Guide to the Duke Artists Series records, 1931-2000 UA.07.05.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Artists Series records
1931-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Duke Artists Series
UA.07.05.0001
9 Linear Feet
The Duke Artists Series, founded in 1931, brings international music, opera, and dance performances to University venues. The Duke Artists Series was administered by the Office of Cultural Affairs and later, the Office of University Life. This collection includes programs, printed matter, correspondence, clippings, artist contracts, financial materials, and box office reports. Major subjects include Duke University, the Duke Artists Series, the Office of Cultural Affairs, the Office of University Life, and performing arts. Materials range in date from 1931-2000. English.
6,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Transfer; 2000; A2000-65.
Transfer; 2002; A2002-35.
Historical Note
The Artists Series was founded in 1931, when an unfortunate fire at Raleigh's Memorial Auditorium forced a scheduled concert by piano great Ignace Paderewski to be moved to Duke's Page Auditorium. Paderewski played to an enthusiastic crowd, albeit in near complete dark due to his stage fright, and in the midst of a winter snowstorm. After its unscheduled beginning, the Artists Series soon became a cultural institution on campus and in the community. From the start, the Series presented established and admired international performers in classical music, opera, ballet, and folk and modern dance.
Each academic year, an average of six performances have been scheduled, primarily in Page Auditorium, although Cameron Indoor Stadium has been used for unusually large or popular performing groups such as the New York Philharmonic Orchestra. Examples of artists who have performed as part of the Artists Series include Jascha Heifetz, the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, Yehudi Menuhin, Artur Rubinstein, Martha Graham, the Robert Shaw Chorale, Andres Segovia, Isaac Stern, Beverly Sills, Leontyne Price, and Murray Perahia amongst many others. The Artists Series was directed from its inception to 1956 by J. Foster Barnes, Director of Social and Religious Affairs. William J. Griffith, Director of the Student Union and later of Student Affairs, led the Series from 1956 to 1969 when Ella Fountain Pratt took over its leadership under the Office of Cultural Affairs. Upon Pratt's retirement in 1984, Susan L. Coon, as Director of the Office of Cultural Affairs, assumed administration of the program. As of the 2000-2001 academic year, the Artists Series is administered by Coon under the Office of University Life. There is an advisory committee chaired by the Director of the Office of Cultural Affairs (or University Life). The ten member committee is composed of at least two members of the Music Department, two general faculty, two members of the community, four students from the major dance and music organizations, and the chairperson of the University Union Performing Arts Committee. The advisory committee is responsible for the final selection of series performers and the approval financial arrangements accompanying these selections.
Collection Overview
Contains programs, printed matter, correspondence and artists contracts, and financial and box office reports pertaining to the Duke Artists Series. Materials range in date from 1931-2000.
Related Material
Office of Cultural Affairs records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Office of University Life records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Performing Arts -- United States; Duke University. Duke Artists Series; Duke University. Duke Artists Series; Duke University. Office of Cultural Affairs; Duke University. Office of University Life
- Subject Files, 1931-1990
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains administration and management materials including correspondence, financial statements and box office reports, a brief history of the series, advisory committee minutes, and lists of the series performers. Also includes contracts, correspondence, publicity materials, box office reports, and newspaper clippings.
  Arrangement note
  Ordered alphabetically by topic.
  - Advisory Committee, 1955-1969 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee, 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Barnes, J. Foster, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Cancellations, 1969-1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1990 (Box 1)
  - Development Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1932-1957 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1958-1969 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Financial Statements, 1973-1984 (Box 1)
  - Form Letters, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising, 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - Group Advertisements, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - History to 2000, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Lists of Artists Series Performers, 1931-1990 (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Arts Council, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Opening Dinner, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Rate of Credit for Tickets, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Usher Corps, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Wagner Affair, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - Seasons
    - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 1)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Duke Artists Series, Budget 1975-1976; 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Duke Artist Series, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Duke Artists Series, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Duke Artists Series, Survey 1983 (Box 3)
  - Duke Artists Series, Box Office Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Duke Artists Series, Board of Directors, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - NC Arts Council Dance Touring Program Grants Evaluation Forms, 1979- (Box 3)
  - Grant Requests: NC Arts Council/Duke Artists Series (Box 3)
  - NC Arts Council, Misc. Grant Information (Box 3)
  - Southern Arts Federation Grant, 1984 (Box 3)
  - NC Arts Council, NC Touring Program, Piedmont Chamber Orchestra (Box 3)
  - Murray Louis Film: "Dance as an Art Form" (Box 3)
  - Lost Eden Production (Box 3)
  - Raleigh's Dream (Box 3)
  - Artists Series Contribution, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Fundraising Event, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Artist Series, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Contributions, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Contributions, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Dinner Invitation, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Artist Series Contributions, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Faculty/Employee Discount for Cultural Events, 1990-1992 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Contributions, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Artist Series Fundraising, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Artist Series Misc. Publicity, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Nicholas Kitchen, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Czech Philharmonic, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Richard Stoltzman, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Samuel Ramey, 1991 (Box 4)
  - NY Baroque Dance Co. and Concert Royal, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Academy of St. Martin in the Fields, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Brochure, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Contributions, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Murray Perahia, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Empire Brass, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Frederica Von Stade, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Orchestra of the Eighteenth Century, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Royal Winnipeg Ballet, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Kyung Wha Chung, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Emanual Ax and Yo Yo Ma, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Western Opera Theater - "La Boheme," 1992 (Box 4)
  - Royal New Zealand Ballet, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Dawn Upshaw, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Joshua Bell, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Danish Radio National Symphony Orchestra with Bella Davidovich, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Contributions, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Artist Series, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Donors, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Mark Morris Dance Group, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Bolshoi Symphony, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Haken Hagegard, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Orpheus Chamber Orchestra, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Boys Choir of Harlem, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Nadja Salerno-Sonnenberg, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Cho-Liang Lin, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Artists Series Budget, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Vladimir Feltsman, 1994 (Box 4)
  - James Galway, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Chanticleer, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Chamber Orchestra Kremlin 1995 (Box 4)
  - Ballet Theatre de Bordeaux, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Frederica Von Stade, 1995 (Box 4)
- Printed Materials, 1930-1999
  Includes performance brochures, flyers, performance programs for each featured artist, and seasonal brochures.
  Ordered chronologically.
  - Seasons
    - 1930-1931 (Box 5)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 5)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 5)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 5)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 5)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 5)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 5)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 5)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 5)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 5)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 5)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 5)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 5)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 5)
- Photographs, 1931-1984
  Contains publicity photographs sent to Duke University by performer agencies and managers.
  - 1931-1949; n.d. (Box 6)
  - 1950-1960 Spring (Box 6)
  - 1960 Fall -1963 Spring (Box 6)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Negatives (Box 6)